<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>R Markdown on Simina blog</title>
    <link>/tags/r-markdown/</link>
    <description>Recent content in R Markdown on Simina blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 07 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/r-markdown/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Bayes&#39;s rule in practice: CF carrier testing</title>
      <link>/2019/02/07/bayes-s-rule-in-practice-cf-carrier-testing/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/02/07/bayes-s-rule-in-practice-cf-carrier-testing/</guid>
      <description>Cystic fibrosis (CF) is a recessive genetic disorder which is the most common life-limiting genetic disorder amongst Caucasians. I have written before about how improved management of the disease has led to substantial improvements in life expectancy and quality of life, in large part due to its inclusion in newborn screening programs. More recently, it is becoming increasingly common to also offer pregnant women a genetic test to see if they are carriers of a mutation in the CFTR gene.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Everything in statistical modeling can be seen as a regression</title>
      <link>/2018/01/10/everything-in-statistical-modeling-can-be-seen-as-a-regression/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/01/10/everything-in-statistical-modeling-can-be-seen-as-a-regression/</guid>
      <description>This is of course a bit of an exaggeration! It also depends on the way things are emphasized in, for example, statisticalgraduate programs. I know that my own training program was highly focused on seeing much of statistics as either aspecial case or a generalization of some kind of linear regression model. I kind of love this view and try to emphasize it whenever I canto collaborators, although I do admit that sometimes you have to start from special cases in order to build up the whole.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>